I'm a veteran of the starship Enterprise.
أنا متمرس في المغامرات الفضائية.
I soared through the galaxy
حلقت عبر المجرة
driving a huge starship
أقود سفينة فضائية ضخمة
with a crew made up of people
مع طاقم من الناس
from all over this world,
من مختلف أنحاء العالم،
many different races, many different cultures,
أعراق مختلفة، وثقافات مختلفة،
many different heritages,
وموروثات مختلفة،
all working together,
كلنا نعمل سويًا،
and our mission was to explore strange new worlds,
وكانت مهمتنا اكشاف عوالم جديدة غريبة،
to seek out new life and new civilizations,
للبحث عن حياة جديدة وحضارات جديدة
to boldly go where no one has gone before.
لنذهب بجسارة إلى حيث لم يصل أحد من قبل
Well —
حسنًا ـــــ
(Applause) —
(تصفيق)ـــــ
I am the grandson of immigrants from Japan
أنا حفيد لمهاجرين من اليابان
who went to America,
ذهبوا إلى أمريكا،
boldly going to a strange new world,
بجسارة ذاهبون إلى عالم جديد غريب،
seeking new opportunities.
باحثون عن فرص جديدة
My mother was born in Sacramento, California.
وُلدت أمي في سكرامنتو، كاليفورنيا.
My father was a San Franciscan.
كان والدي سان فرانسيسكي.
They met and married in Los Angeles,
التقيا وتزوجا في لوس أنجلوس،
and I was born there.
ووُلدت هناك.
I was four years old
كنت في الرابعة من عمري
when Pearl Harbor was bombed
حين قصفت اليابان ميناء بيرل هاربر
on December 7, 1941 by Japan,
في 7 ديسمبر 1941،
and overnight, the world was plunged
وبين عشية وضحاها أُقحم العالم
into a world war.
في حرب عالمية.
America suddenly was swept up
اجتاحت الهستيريا
by hysteria.
أمريكا فجأة.
Japanese-Americans,
اليابانيون الأمريكيون،
American citizens of Japanese ancestry,
مواطنون أمريكيون من أصل ياباني،
were looked on
كانوا مراقبين
with suspicion and fear
بشك وخوف
and with outright hatred
وكره مطلق
simply because we happened to look like
لأننا ببساطة صادف أننا كنا نبدو مثل
the people that bombed Pearl Harbor.
الناس الذين قصفوا ميناء بيرل هاربر.
And the hysteria grew and grew
ونَمت الهستريا أكثر وأكثر
until in February 1942,
حتي فبراير 1942،
the president of the United States,
حين أمر رئيس الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية،
Franklin Delano Roosevelt,
فرانكلين ديلانو روزفيلت،
ordered all Japanese-Americans
باعتقال كل اليبانيين الأمريكيين
on the West Coast of America
في الساحل الغربي الأمريكي
to be summarily rounded up
بشكل فوري
with no charges, with no trial,
من غير تهم ولا محاكمة،
with no due process.
ومن غير اتباع إجراءات التقاضي الصحيحة.
Due process, this is a core pillar
إجراءات التقاضي الصحيحة هي العمود الأساسي
of our justice system.
في نظامنا القضائي.
That all disappeared.
والذي اختفى تمامًا.
We were to be rounded up
تم اعتقالنا
and imprisoned in 10 barbed-wire prison camps
و سجننا في 10 معسكرات اعتقال محاطة بأسلاك شائكة
in some of the most desolate places in America:
في أكثر الأماكن المقفرة في أميركا:
the blistering hot desert of Arizona,
في صحراء أريزونا شديدة السخونة،
the sultry swamps of Arkansas,
مستنقعات أركنساس الخانقة،
the wastelands of Wyoming, Idaho, Utah, Colorado,
في الأراضي المقفرة في وايومينج، وأيدوها، ويوتاه، وكولورادوا،
and two of the most desolate places in California.
و اثنين من أكثر الأماكن المهجورة في كاليفورنيا.
On April 20th, I celebrated my fifth birthday,
في 20 أبريل احتفلت بعيد ميلادي الخامس،
and just a few weeks after my birthday,
وبعد عيد ميلادي بأسابيع قليلة،
my parents got my younger brother,
أيقظنا والدانا أنا وأخي الأصغر،
my baby sister and me
و أختي الرضيعة
up very early one morning,
مبكرا جدا ذات صباح،.
and they dressed us hurriedly.
وألبسانا على عجلٍ.
My brother and I were in the living room
كنت وأخي في غرفة المعيشة
looking out the front window,
ننظر من النافذة الأمامية،
and we saw two soldiers marching up our driveway.
ورأينا جنديين يمشيان في الطريق إلى منزلنا.
They carried bayonets on their rifles.
كانا يحملان بنادق ذات خناجر.
They stomped up the front porch
تقدما حتى الشرفة الأمامية
and banged on the door.
ودقا على الباب.
My father answered it,
أجابهم أبي،
and the soldiers ordered us out of our home.
أمرنا الجنود أن نخرج من منزلنا.
My father gave my brother and me
أعطاني أبي أنا و أخي
small luggages to carry,
حقائب صغيرة لنحملها،
and we walked out and stood on the driveway
وخرجنا ووقفنا عند المدخل
waiting for our mother to come out,
ننتظر خروج أمي،
and when my mother finally came out,
وحين خرجت أمي أخيرًا،
she had our baby sister in one arm,
كانت تحمل أختي الرضيعة على ذراع،
a huge duffel bag in the other,
وحقيبة قماش ضخمة على الآخر،
and tears were streaming down both her cheeks.
وكانت الدموع تنهمر على وجنتيها.
I will never be able to forget that scene.
لن يكن بمقدوري أبدًا أن أنسى ذلك المشهد.
It is burned into my memory.
إنه محفور في ذاكرتي.
We were taken from our home
أُخذنا من منزلنا
and loaded on to train cars
وحُملنا على عربات القطار
with other Japanese-American families.
مع عائلات يابانية أمريكية أخرى.
There were guards stationed
كان هناك حراس متمركزون
at both ends of each car,
علي طرفيَّ كل سيارة،
as if we were criminals.
كما لو كنا مجرمين.
We were taken two thirds of the way across the country,
قطعنا ثلثيَّ الطريق عبر البلد،
rocking on that train for four days and three nights,
نتأرجح في القطار لمدة أربعة أيام وثلاث ليال،
to the swamps of Arkansas.
متوجهين إلى مستنقعات أركنساس.
I still remember the barbed wire fence
لازلت أتذكر السياج الشائك
that confined me.
الذي كان يحبسني.
I remember the tall sentry tower
أتذكر أبراج الحراسة العالية
with the machine guns pointed at us.
وعليها أسلحة رشاشة موجهة إلينا.
I remember the searchlight that followed me
أتذكر الكشافات التي كانت تتبعني
when I made the night runs
حين كنت أقضي الليل جريًا
from my barrack to the latrine.
من ثكنتي للمرحاض.
But to five-year-old me,
لكن بالنسبة لي أنا ذو الخمسة أعوام،
I thought it was kind of nice that they'd lit the way
كنت أعتقدت أن من اللطيف أنهم يضيئون الطريق
for me to pee.
لي لكي أتبول.
I was a child,
كنت طفلًا،
too young to understand the circumstances
صغيرًا جدًا لأستوعب ملابسات
of my being there.
وجودي هناك.
Children are amazingly adaptable.
الأطفال قادرون على التكيف بشكلٍ مذهلٍ.
What would be grotesquely abnormal
ما يمكن أن يكون غير طبيعي غريب
became my normality
أصبح يمثل طبيعتي
in the prisoner of war camps.
في معسكرات أسرى الحرب.
It became routine for me to line up three times a day
أصبح من المعتاد أن اصطف ثلاث مرات يوميًا
to eat lousy food in a noisy mess hall.
لتناول طعام ردئ في قاعة طعام تعمها الفوضى والضوضاء.
It became normal for me to go with my father
أصبح من العادي أن أذهب مع أبي
to bathe in a mass shower.
لنقوم بالاستحمام في حمام جماعي.
Being in a prison, a barbed-wire prison camp,
كوني في سجن، معسكر اعتقال محاط بالأسلاك الشائكة،
became my normality.
أصبح يمثل طبيعتي.
When the war ended,
حين انتهت الحرب،
we were released,
أطلقوا سراحنا،
and given a one-way ticket
وأعطونا تذكرة ذهاب بلا عودة
to anywhere in the United States.
لأي مكان في الولايات المتحدة.
My parents decided to go back home
قرر أبي وأمي العودة إلى ديارهم
to Los Angeles,
إلي لوس أنجلوس،
but Los Angeles was not a welcoming place.
لكن لم تكن لوس أنجلوس مكان ترحيب.
We were penniless.
كنا مفلسين.
Everything had been taken from us,
أُخذ كل شيءٍ مننا،
and the hostility was intense.
وكان العداء شديد.
Our first home was on Skid Row
أول منزلنا كان في سكيد رو
in the lowest part of our city,
في أدنى جزء من مدينتنا،
living with derelicts, drunkards
نعيش مع المنبوذين، والسكارى
and crazy people,
و المجانين،
the stench of urine all over,
رائحة البول في كل مكان،
on the street, in the alley,
في الشارع، وفي الزقاق،
in the hallway.
وفي الممر.
It was a horrible experience,
كانت تجربة بشعة،
and for us kids, it was terrorizing.
ومروعة لنا كأطفال.
I remember once
أتذكر ذات مرة
a drunkard came staggering down,
جاء سكير مترنح،
fell down right in front of us,
وسقط أمامنا تمامًا،
and threw up.
و تقيأ.
My baby sister said, "Mama, let's go back home,"
قالت أختي الصغيرة، "ماما دعينا نعود للبيت،"
because behind barbed wires
لأن خلف الأسلاك الشائكة
was for us
كان بالنسبة لنا
home.
البيت.
My parents worked hard
عمل أبي وأمي بجد
to get back on their feet.
ليقفا على قدميهما.
We had lost everything.
كنا قد فقدنا كل شئ.
They were at the middle of their lives
وكانا في منتصف حياتهما
and starting all over.
ويبتديان من جديد.
They worked their fingers to the bone,
عملا بكل جهدهما،
and ultimately they were able
وفي نهاية المطاف تمكنا
to get the capital together to buy
سويًا من الحصول على المال لشراء
a three-bedroom home in a nice neighborhood.
منزل من ثلاث غرف نوم في حي جميل.
And I was a teenager,
وكنت في سن المراهقة،
and I became very curious
وأصبحت فضولي جدًا
about my childhood imprisonment.
حول سجن طفولتي
I had read civics books that told me about
قرأت كتب الحقوق المدنية التي أخبرتني عن
the ideals of American democracy.
المثل العليا للديموقراطية الأمريكية.
All men are created equal,
خُلق كل الناس سواسية،
we have an inalienable right
لنا حق لا يمكن مصادرته
to life, liberty and the pursuit of happiness,
للحياة، والحرية، والسعي وراء السعادة،
and I couldn't quite make that fit
و لم أستطيع أن أجعل هذا يلائم تمامًا
with what I knew to be my childhood imprisonment.
وما أعرفه عن سجن طفولتي.
I read history books,
قرأت كتب التاريخ،
and I couldn't find anything about it.
و لم أستطيع إيجاد أي شيء عنها.
And so I engaged my father after dinner
ولذلك شاركت أبي بعد العشاء
in long, sometimes heated conversations.
في مناقشة طويلة، تحتدم أحيانًا.
We had many, many conversations like that,
جرت بيننا حوارات كثيرة مثل هذه،
and what I got from them
وما حصلت عليه منهم
was my father's wisdom.
كان حكمة أبي.
He was the one that suffered the most
كان أكثر من عانى
under those conditions of imprisonment,
في ظل ظروف السجن هذه،
and yet he understood American democracy.
ومع ذلك فهم الديموقراطية الأمريكية.
He told me that our democracy
أخبرني أن ديموقراطيتنا
is a people's democracy,
هي ديموقراطية الشعب.
and it can be as great as the people can be,
ويمكن أن تكون عظيمة كما للشعب أن يكون،
but it is also as fallible as people are.
لكنها غير معصومة كما الشعب أيضًا.
He told me that American democracy
أخبرني أن الديموقراطية الأمريكية
is vitally dependent on good people
معتمدة بشكل حيوي علي الأناس الجيدين
who cherish the ideals of our system
الذين يعتزون بالمثل العليا لنظامنا
and actively engage in the process
ويشاركون بنشاط في عملية
of making our democracy work.
جعل ديموقراطيتنا تعمل.
And he took me to a campaign headquarters —
وأخذني لمقر الحملة الرئيسي ـــ
the governor of Illinois was running for the presidency —
حاكم الينويز كان مترشحًا للرئاسة ـــ
and introduced me to American electoral politics.
وأدخلني إلى السياسة الانتخابية الأميركية.
And he also told me about
وأخبرني أيضًا عن
young Japanese-Americans
الشباب الياباني الأمريكي
during the Second World War.
خلال الحرب العالمية الثانية.
When Pearl Harbor was bombed,
حين تم قصف ميناء بيرل هاربر،
young Japanese-Americans, like all young Americans,
الشباب الياباني الأمريكي، مثل كل الشباب الأمريكي،
rushed to their draft board
هرعوا إلى مراكز التطوع في الجيش
to volunteer to fight for our country.
للتطوع للقتال في سبيل بلدنا.
That act of patriotism
هذا العمل الوطني
was answered with a slap in the face.
تم الرد عليه بلطمة علي الوجه.
We were denied service,
تم منعنا من الخدمة في الجيش،
and categorized as enemy non-alien.
و تم تصنيفنا كعدو غير أجنبي.
It was outrageous to be called an enemy
كان أمرًا مهينا أن تدعى عدو
when you're volunteering to fight for your country,
في الوقت الذي تتطوع فيه للقتال من أجل بلدك،
but that was compounded with the word "non-alien,"
لكن ذلك كان مرتبط بكلمة "غير أجنبي،"
which is a word that means
والتي تعني
"citizen" in the negative.
"مواطن" غير فعال.
They even took the word "citizen" away from us,
حتى كلمة "مواطن" أخذوها مننا،
and imprisoned them for a whole year.
و سجنوهم لسنة كاملة.
And then the government realized
ثم أدركت الحكومة
that there's a wartime manpower shortage,
أن هناك نقص في القوة البشرية وقت الحرب،
and as suddenly as they'd rounded us up,
وكما قاموا باعتقالنا فجأة،
they opened up the military for service
قاموا بفتح باب التطوع في الجيش فجأة
by young Japanese-Americans.
للشباب الياباني الأمريكي.
It was totally irrational,
وقد كان أمرًا غير منطقي تمامًا،
but the amazing thing,
لكن الشيء المدهش،
the astounding thing,
الشيء المذهل،
is that thousands of young
أن آلاف الشباب
Japanese-American men and women
الياباني الأمريكي رجال ونساء
again went from behind those barbed-wire fences,
ذهبوا مرة أخرى من خلف تلك الأسوار الشائكة،
put on the same uniform as that of our guards,
وارتدوا نفس الزي الرسمي لحراسنا،
leaving their families in imprisonment,
تاركين عائلاتهم في السجن،
to fight for this country.
للقتال من أجل هذه البلد.
They said that they were going to fight
قالوا أنهم ذاهبون للقاتل
not only to get their families out
ليس فقط لإخراج عائلاتهم
from behind those barbed-wire fences,
من خلف تلك الأسوار الشائكة،
but because they cherished the very ideal
لكن أيضًا لأنهم يعتزون بالمثالية الفائقة
of what our government stands for,
بحيث ما تواجهه حكوماتنا،
should stand for,
يجب أن نواجهه،
and that was being abrogated
وذلك كان يجرى إلغائه
by what was being done.
بما كان يتم فعله.
All men are created equal.
خُلق كل البشر سواسية.
And they went to fight for this country.
وذهبوا للقتال من أجل هذه البلد.
They were put into a segregated
وتم وضعهم في معزل
all Japanese-American unit
كل وحدات اليابانيون الأمريكيون
and sent to the battlefields of Europe,
أُرسلت إلى ساحات المعارك في اوروبا،
and they threw themselves into it.
وألقوا أنفسهم فيها.
They fought with amazing,
قاتلوا ببسالة وشجاعة
incredible courage and valor.
مدهشة لا تصدق.
They were sent out on the most dangerous missions
تم إرسالهم لأخطر المهمات
and they sustained the highest combat casualty rate
وتكبدوا نسبيًا أعلى معدل إصابات معارك
of any unit proportionally.
من أي وحدة أخرى.
There is one battle that illustrates that.
هناك معركة أوضحت ذلك.
It was a battle for the Gothic Line.
كانت معركة علي الخط القوطي
The Germans were embedded
تمركز الألمان
in this mountain hillside,
في تلك التلال الجبلية،
rocky hillside,
التلال الصخرية،
in impregnable caves,
في كهوف منيعة،
and three allied battalions
وكانت ثلاث كتائب من الحلفاء
had been pounding away at it
يقصفونهم عن بعد
for six months,
لستة أشهر،
and they were stalemated.
وكانوا مشلولين.
The 442nd was called in
تم استدعاء الوحدة 442 ن د
to add to the fight,
للانضمام للقتال،
but the men of the 442nd
لكن رجال الوحدة 442 ن د
came up with a unique
جائوا بفكرة
but dangerous idea:
فريدة ولكن خطيرة:
The backside of the mountain
الجزء الخلفي من الجبل
was a sheer rock cliff.
كان جرف صخري منحدر.
The Germans thought an attack from the backside
اعتقد الألمان أن الهجوم من الخلف
would be impossible.
سيكون مستحيلًا.
The men of the 442nd decided to do the impossible.
قرر رجال الوحدة 442 ن د فعل المستحيل.
On a dark, moonless night,
في ظلام ليلة غير مقمرة،
they began scaling that rock wall,
بدؤا تسلق الحائط الصخري،
a drop of more than 1,000 feet,
إنحدار أكثر من 1000 قدم،
in full combat gear.
في زي قتال كامل.
They climbed all night long
قاموا بالتسلق طوال الليل
on that sheer cliff.
علي الجرف المنحدر.
In the darkness,
في الظلام،
some lost their handhold
فلتت قبضة بعضهم
or their footing
أو موضع أقدامهم
and they fell to their deaths
وسقطوا ليلقوا حتفهم
in the ravine below.
في أسفل الوادي.
They all fell silently.
سقطوا جميعا بلا صوت.
Not a single one cried out,
لم يصرخ واحد،
so as not to give their position away.
حتى لا يكشفوا عن مكانهم.
The men climbed for eight hours straight,
تسلق الرجال ل8 ساعات متصلة،
and those who made it to the top
وهؤلاء الذين وصلوا القمة
stayed there until the first break of light,
بقوا هناك حتى ظهور أول ضوء،
and as soon as light broke,
وبمجرد ظهور أول ضوء،
they attacked.
قاموا بالهجوم.
The Germans were surprised,
تفاجأ الألمان،
and they took the hill
وسيطروا علي التل
and broke the Gothic Line.
و كسروا الخط القوطي.
A six-month stalemate
شلل لمدة 6 شهور
was broken by the 442nd
كسرته الوحدة 442 ن د
in 32 minutes.
في 32 دقيقة.
It was an amazing act,
كان أداء مذهل،
and when the war ended,
وحين انتهت الحرب،
the 442nd returned to the United States
عادت الوحدة 442 ن د إلى الولايات المتحدة
as the most decorated unit
كأبرز وحدات الجيش
of the entire Second World War.
في الحرب العالمية الثانية بأسرها.
They were greeted back on the White House Lawn
استقبلهم الرئيس ترومان في حديقة البيت الأبيض
by President Truman, who said to them,
وقال لهم،
"You fought not only the enemy
"لم تقاتلوا العدو فقط
but prejudice, and you won."
بل التعصب أيضًا، وقد فزتم."
They are my heroes.
هؤلاء هم أبطالي.
They clung to their belief
تمسكوا بإيمانهم
in the shining ideals of this country,
بالمثل العليا الساطعة لهذة البلد،
and they proved that being an American
وأثبتوا أن كوني أمريكيًا
is not just for some people,
ليس لبعض الناس فقط،
that race is not how we define being an American.
ليس العرق ما نحدد به كوني أمريكيًا.
They expanded what it means to be an American,
لقد وسعوا معنى أن تكون أمريكيًا،
including Japanese-Americans
ليشمل اليابانين الأمريكين
that were feared and suspected and hated.
الذين خشيناهم و شككنا فيهم و كرهناهم.
They were change agents,
كانوا عوامل التغيير،
and they left for me
و تركوا لي
a legacy.
إرث.
They are my heroes
إنهم أبطالي
and my father is my hero,
وأبي هو بطلي،
who understood democracy
الذي فهم الديموقراطية
and guided me through it.
وأرشدني لها.
They gave me a legacy,
أعطوني إرثًا
and with that legacy comes a responsibility,
ويأتي مع هذا الإرث مسئولية،
and I am dedicated
وأنا متفاني
to making my country
لأجعل بلدي
an even better America,
أمريكا أفضل،
to making our government
لأجعل حكومتي
an even truer democracy,
ديموقراطية بشكل حقيقي أكثر،
and because of the heroes that I have
ولأجل الأبطال الذين أملكهم
and the struggles that we've gone through,
والصراعات التي خضناها،
I can stand before you
استطيع أن أقف أمامكم
as a gay Japanese-American,
كأمريكي ياباني مسرور،
but even more than that,
بل وأكثر من هذا،
I am a proud American.
أنا أمريكي فخور.
Thank you very much.
أشكركم جزيلًا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)